Register of the Jules Feldmans Papers, 1919-1955
Hoover Institution Archives
Jules Feldmans Papers,
1919-1955
73011
Feldmans, Jules, 1919-1955
18 manuscript boxes, 1 envelope (7.6 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, memoranda, and reports, relating to the Russian occupation of the Baltic states in 1940, displaced persons in Germany, immigration, and Latvian emigre organizations after World War II.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1973.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Access Points
Latvians in foreign countries.; Refugees.; World War, 1939-1945.; World War, 1939-1945--Baltic States.; World War, 1939-1945--Refugees.; Baltic States.; Latvia.; Latvia--History--Soviet occupation, 1940-1941.; Germany.; Soviet Union.; Diplomats--Latvia.
Biographical Note
1889, July 21 Born, Nigranda, Latvia
1915 Graduate, University of Moscow
1919-1921 Legal adviser, chief of Russian Division, Ministry of Foreign Affairs of Latvia
1921 Secretary, Latvian Legation in Paris
1923 Chief, League of Nations Division, Ministry of Foreign Affairs, Riga
1925 Counselor, Latvian Legation, Paris
1925-1927 Charge d'Affaires ad interim
1928-1930 Chief, Eastern and Western Divisions, Riga
1930 Latvian permanent delegate to League of Nations, Geneva
1932 E.E. and M.P. to Switzerland
1939 Latvian envoy to King of Denmark
1949-1953 Minister Plenipotentiary, Charge d'Affaires of Latvia, Washington, D.C.
1953, August 16 Died
Series Description
- Correspondence, 1929-1953. (Box No. 1-4.)
  Correspondence, arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent.
- Subject file, 1919-1951. (Box No. 4-8.)
  Correspondence, memoranda, manuscripts, notes, printed matter, etc. arranged alphabetically by subject.
- Speeches & Writings. (Box No. 8.)
  Speeches and writings arranged alphabetically by title of speech or article.
- Miscellaneous. (Box No. 8-18.)
  Clippings arranged chronologically by year.
Container List
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1929-1953
  - Agence Telegraphique Suisse. Societe anonyme, 1948 (Box 1.)
  - Alberts, Pols, 1945
  - Alksins, A., 1947
  - Alksins, Klara Maria, 1947
  - Ambassade de France, Berne, 1945
  - Aubert, M. Theodore, (President, Entente Internationale Anticommuniste), 1947
  - Balodis, P., 1943
  - Baltic Committee, Memmingen, 1948-1949
  - Baltic Welfare, Educational and Employment Organization, 1947-1949
  - Bankevics, Janis, 1947
  - Bardins, J., 1949
  - Berzins, L., 1946
  - Berzinsh, Alexander, 1948
  - Bidault, Georges, 1946
  - Biddle, Colonel Anthony J., 1948
  - Bilmanis, Alfred, 1946-1948
  - Bonna, P., 1941
  - Brazilian Latvian Aid Committee, 1948
  - Brunner, Dr., 1945
  - Burckhardt, Dr. K., 1945
  - Camans, J., 1946
  - Ceichners, A., 1944
  - Celma, J., 1948
  - Churchill, Winston, 1945
  - Clement, Lt., 1944
  - Comision De Cooperacion Baltica De Immigracion. Buenos Aires, 1948
  - Conseil Central de Lettonie, 1946
  - De Steiger, Ed, 1945
  - Dinbergs, Anatol, 1948
  - Don Suisse Pour les Victimes de la Guerre, 1945
  - D. P. Center "Valka", 1948
  - Dravnieks, Dr. Ing. Ernests, 1948
  - Du Bochet, P. (Tribune de Geneve), 1943-1944
  - Ducmans, K., 1929
  - Dzintars, Karlis-Karlo, 1947
  - Edgars, T., 1946
  - Etter, Dr. Ph. (Bundesprasident, Berne), 1946
  - Evaldson, O., 1946
  - Foreign Students Association in the British Zone of Germany, 1948
  - Fraivalds, Ev., 1947
  - Frey, Dr. S., 1948
  - Gayda, Virginio (Directeur du Giornale d'Italia), 1941
  - Golaz, Pilet (President de la Confederation, Berne), 1940-1941
  - Grava, V., 1948
  - Gorsvalds, O., 1946, 1953
  - Gulbis, Prof. F., 1952
  - Hambro, C. J., 1946-1947
  - Harrison, Leland, 1943, 1946
  - Hellstrom, Oscar, 1949
  - Hermanis, Fritz, 1946-1947
  - Institut Universaire du Hautes Etudes Internationales, 1940
  - International Committee, 1945
  - International Refugee Organization, 1948-1949
  - Jaundzems, S., 1948
  - Joelsons, N. R., 1951
  - Jones, John, 1947
  - Kacens, A., 1947 (Box 2.)
  - Kaliksons, 1948
  - Kalinina, Dr. Paul - FONDS, 1946, 1948
  - Kalnins, Bruno & P., 1945, 1947-1948
  - Kalnins, Dr. P., 1945
  - Kampus, R., 1953
  - Keller, Dr. A. (Der Bund, Berne), 1944
  - Klarks, H., 1948
  - Klavins-Ellanski, J., 1944-1947
  - Klavsons, A., 1948
  - Kreenwinsch, Dr. Edgar, 1946
  - Kreicbergs, Valdemars, 1948
  - Kroders, A., 1945-1946
  - Kukainis, Robert, 1949
  - Kundzins, K., 1946
  - Laipniek, Jekabs, 1946
  - Lambergs, V. (Chairman, Latvian Central Committee), 1948-1949, 1952
  - Latvian Aid Committee, 1945-1947
  - Latvian Aid Committee in Denmark, 1945-1946
  - Latvian Association in Tyrol, 1946
  - Latvian Belgian Association, 1948
  - Latvian Central Committee, 1945, 1947-1949
  - Latvian Central Council, 1948
  - Latvian Committee, Ansbach/Hindenburg - Post, 1948
  - Latvian Consul General in Berne, 1945
  - Latvian Consul General in Czechoslovakia, 1930
  - Latvian District Committee in Austria, 1946-1948
  - Latvian District Committee of Bavaria, 1948
  - Latvian District Committee Wurttemberg-Baden, 1947-1948
  - Latvian Legation in Washington D.C., 1950
  - Latvian Medical Union, 1948
  - Latvian National Committee, 1940, 1947
  - Latvian National Council. Presidium, 1948
  - Latvian National Fund (Sweden), 1948-1949
  - Latvian News Bulletin, 1946
  - Latvian Republics Parliament. Presidium, 1948
  - Latvian Students Group at the University Bonn, 1947
  - Latvian Swedish Society, 1945-1946, 1948
  - "Latvju Zinu" 1945, 1949
  - Le Verrier, Madelein, 1939
  - Lie, Trygve (Secretary-General, UN), 1948
  - Ludi, M., 1941
  - Mac Kittrick, M. (President, Banque des Reglements Internationaux), 1940
  - Maeder, Dr., 1945
  - Maizite, V., 1946
  - Martin, Jean, 1943
  - Millers, V., 1946
  - Munters, V., 1939-1940
  - Nikurs, Robert, 1947-1949 (Box 3.)
  - Norton, Clifford John, 1943-1944
  - Ozolins, K., 1945-1947
  - Ozolins, P., 1948
  - Perkons, Janis, 1945
  - Petitpierre, Max, 1945
  - Pittard, M., 1945
  - Podniers, E., 1946
  - Prieditis, Dr. G., 1948
  - Prieditis, P., 1946
  - Rancanam, Biskapam J., 1948
  - Red Cross, 1944-1949
  - Reinfelds, Remans, 1945-1946, 1948 (Box 4.)
  - Reters, R., 1946
  - Roosevelt, Franklin D., 1943-1944
  - Roze, Dr. E., 1948
  - Salnais, V., 1945
  - Scavenius, E., 1940
  - Schwarz, Helena, 1948
  - Scottish League for European Freedom, 1948
  - Service Social des Personnes Deplacees en Vorarlberg, 1946
  - Siktara, O., 1948
  - Silis, O., 1948
  - Skulte, W., 1948
  - Sleire, Dagnija, 1953
  - Smallwood, J. R., 1948
  - Stadler, Monsieur, 1944
  - Stelling-Michaud, S. (Redaction, Journal de Geneve), 1943
  - Stepans, Janis, 1947
  - Sues, Marcel, 1946
  - Svabes, A., 1946
  - Tepfers, J., 1953
  - Terrise, R., 1943
  - Tivumnieks, P., 1948
  - Trapans, V., 1948-1949
  - Truman, Harry S., 1953
  - Turauskas, Edouard, 1944
  - Turks, Janis, 1948-1949
  - Unden, M., 1945
  - Union of Latvian People, 1948
  - United Kingdom. Foreign Office, 1946
  - U.S. Department of State, 1941, 1946, 1948
  - Upitis, Peteris, 1947
  - Valdmanis, Alfred, 1945, 1948
  - Valters, Mikelis, 1946
  - Varsbergs, J., 1945-1946
  - Veinbergs, Rev. A. (Pastor, Latvian Lutheran Church, Washington, D.C.), 1953
  - Vennera, J., 1948
  - Vitola, V., 1947-1948
  - Zadeikis, Povilas, 1948
  - Zarins, K., 1945-1948, 1953
  - Miscellaneous
- SUBJECT FILE, 1919-1951
  - Agreement between Estonia and Svenska Tandsticks Aktienbolaget, 1928 (Box 4.)
  - Agreement between Estonia and Svenska Tandsticks Aktienbolaget, 1928
  - "Aicinajums", 1948
  - American Zone - Invalid Register
  - Baltic Central Council. Latvian Representative, 1949
  - Baltic D. P. Camp "Daugava" at Melle, 1948
  - Baltic Humanitarian Association, 1948
  - Baltic Independence
  - Baltic Independence (Box 5.)
  - Baltic Women's Council, 1948
  - "Bankruptcy of the League of Nations", 1939
  - Bilmanis, Alfred
  - Biographical Data on the Leaders of the Contact Group in Sweden of the Underground National Guerilla and Resistance Movement in Latvia
  - Blaumanis, P., 1948
  - "Burtnieks Landekas Latviesu Laikrasts", 1945: #1, 2
  - Camp Fishbach, 1940
  - Council of the Latvian Assembly Center, Esslingen, 1948
  - Czechoslovakia, 1941
  - "Czechoslovakia" by Constantin Fotitch, 1948
  - Danish Red Cross, 1946, 1949
  - "Derriere Le Rideau de Fer"
  - Displaced Persons
  - Displaced Persons (Box 6.)
  - "East Europe", August 14, 1946
  - "Entente Internationale Anticommuniste", June, 1946
  - Estonian, Latvian and Lithuanian Refugee Committees in Germany, 1948
  - Food Rations of Refugees from the Baltic States, 1945
  - Germany: Criminal Punishment, 1946
  - Germany: Railroad Employees, 1943
  - Germany: Traveling Regulations, 1946
  - Government of India. Information Services, 1948
  - "Il ne faut pas oublier les etats Baltes" by Birger Newman
  - Intelligence Division. Frankfurt, 1947
  - International Conference of Social Democrat Parties. London, 1946
  - International Red Cross, 1946
  - International Refugee Organization
  - Jurevics, Professor P., 1949
  - Koppe, Wilhelm
  - Latvia
    - Agrarian Reforms
    - Commerce Agreement with the Soviet Union, 1927
    - Diplomatic and Consular Representatives, List of, 1946
    - Economic Conditions, 1945
    - Minorities
    - Miscellaneous
  - "Latvia Under Bolshevik Yoke" (Box 7.)
  - Latvian Aid Committee in Austria, 1947
  - Latvian Alliance Organization, 1948
  - Latvian Assembly in Esslingen, 1949
  - Latvian Central Committee
  - Latvian Central Committee. Information Bulletin, 1949
  - Latvian Central Council, 1947-1949
  - Latvian Information Bulletin, July, 1946
  - Latvian National Committee
  - Latvian National Council
  - Latvian National Fund (Sweden)
  - Latvian Prisoners of War in Italy
  - Latvian Relief, Inc.
  - Latvian Resistance Against Russian Occupation
  - Latvian String Quartet, 1946
  - "Latvju Domas"- 1943-44: #1-12
  - Lazda, Zinaida, 1949
  - "Life in a Soviet Concentration Camp"
  - List of Latvian Persons Interned in Sweden and, on January 24, 1946, Surrendered to the USSR
  - Lithuanian Political Prisoners
  - Lithuanians in America
  - Maps
  - Meeting of Military Representatives of Central and Eastern European Nations, Resolutions. Paris, 1951
  - "Memorandum of Information on Foreign Affairs and the World Crisis", 1940
  - Organization Internationale Pour Les Refugees, 1949
  - Ozols, Nikoajs (Pastor for Latvian Refugees), 1949
  - Poland
  - "Polish Fortnightly Review", 1940: #9
  - "La Propriete Privee dans les Etats Baltes", 1943
  - "Protocols of the Elders of Zion", 1934-1935
  - "Questions Lithuaniennes Documentation Fascicule" - #11
  - Radio Broadcasts, 1948
  - Red Cross (Box 8.)
  - Report by Albert Kalme, Representative in the USA of the Latvian Resistance Movement, to the CIA, regarding Latvian Anti-Soviet Organizations, etc., New York, 1949
  - "Report on Latvia"
  - Ribbentrop
  - "Riga, Decline of a City"
  - Siberian Army, 1919
  - Sikorski, General - Extracts from an address in London, March 30, 1943
  - "Situation in Latvia"
  - "Situation in the Baltic States in March 1943 According to Finnish Sources" by J. Valdmanis
  - "The Situation of Baltic Citizens in Danzig Poland", 1946
  - Skreenbers, Arnold
  - "Society, News and Information on Latvian Refugees in Sweden" by A. Kelderis
  - "Soviet Armed Forces Against Latvia in 1939-1940"
  - Soviet Union
  - Swedish Latvian Relief Committee
  - Trains on which Latvians were sent to the USSR, June 1941
  - Ulmanis, Karlis
  - Union De Banques Suisses, 1947
  - Union of Latvian Camps, Franken District, 1948
  - UN 3rd Assembly, Appeals from Baltic States, 1948
  - UNRRA U.S. Zone. Headquarters, Heidelberg
  - Waffen - Standartenfuhrer Lobe, 1944
  - "Where Are We Going?"
  - Zarins, K.
  - Zemskii Meeting, Irkutsk - Resolutions passed, July 9, 1919
  - Miscellaneous documents
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS
  - "International Situation", 1939 (Box 8.)
  - "Projet de Memorandum sur la Neutralite de la Suisse au sein de la Societe des Nations"
  - Miscellaneous drafts & notes
- MISCELLANEOUS
  - Clippings (Box 8.)
    - 1930-1932
    - 1932-1940 (Box 9.)
    - 1930-1941 (Box 10.)
    - 1942-1946 (Box 11.)
    - 1946-1950 (Box 12.)
    - 1948-1950 (Box 13.)
    - 1950 (Box 14.)
    - 1950-1952, 1955 (Box 15.)
    - Various dates (Box 16.)
    - Various dates (Box 17.)
    - Various dates (Box 18.)